Finding Aid for Institute of Science and Technology (University of Michigan) records, 1950-1989.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Institute of Science and Technology (University of Michigan) records
1950-1989
University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.
90132 Bimu C147 2
University of Michigan scientific research center. Office files relating to the activities of the unit, and to the research divisions that IST administered, notably the Willow Run Laboratories, the Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center, the University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute, and others.
33 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records (donor no. 5993 ) were transferred to the Michigan Historical Collections in 1989-1990.
The collection is open to research.
The Institute of Science and Technology (hereafter called IST) was established in 1959 by the Regents of the University of Michigan as a research center to link the scientific and technological expertise of the university's faculty to specific research initiatives that would prove beneficial to the state's economy. IST marked a new approach to cooperative research efforts. For the first time, a state government designated funds specifically for the purpose of encouraging scientific research activity.
In practice, IST was a nurturer of scientific research and education, serving as a facilitator agency, organizing interdisciplinary teams of faculty and students to undertake major projects with government or industrial support. Beyond this, IST was the homebase for a number of interdisciplinary research and service units that had been created to support the state's industrial climate. Initially, these area units consisted only of the Great Lakes Research Institute and the Biophysics Research Divisions, both of which had been transferred over from the Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies in 1960. A far more important administrative change (also implemented in 1960) was the transfer to IST of responsibility for Willow Run Laboratories (hereafter called WRL). With Willow Run thirteen units were added to IST's growing family of research departments: Analog Computer, Computation, Countermeasures, Engineering Psychology, Fluid and Solid Mechanics, Information Processing, Infrared, Navigation and Guidance, Operations Research, Radar, Sensory Subsystems, Solid-State Physics, and Special Projects.
Because, with the merger, IST assumed responsibility for the records that had been maintained by WRL, a summary discussion of that unit's history and mission seems in order. Willow Run Laboratories originated in 1946 when the University of Michigan, at the request of the U.S. War Department, created the Aeronautical Research Center (ARC) for the purpose of conducting research into the development of the United States air defense capability. Initially, this research centered on problems of defense against the V-2 ballistic missile. Later on, research shifted to the technical feasibility of a defense system against intercontinental ballistic missiles.
The name of the unit was changed to Willow Run Research Center on August 19, 1950 and to Willow Run Laboratories in the Spring of 1955. In 1953, there was a shift in emphasis of the work being done at Willow Run, away from the technology of air defense and a movement toward the study of problems associated with military reconnaissance and surveillance. The focus of this new emphasis was Project MICHIGAN, a long-term research development program to examine applications of modern technology to battlefield situations. In the 1960s, WRL began its important work with the study of ballistic missile radiation phenomenology. This aspect of the science of remote sensing was broadened at this time with various investigations into how the technology underlying airborne reconnaissance and surveillance could be used in detecting, surveying, and monitoring various features related to earth resources and the environment
In the early 1970s, the university made the decision to cease its formal relationship with WRL. In its place, the State Legislature of Michigan, on June 30, 1972, established the Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (ERIM). As set up, ERIM was intended to provide a new structure for the research programs that had been conducted by WRL. With this act of the legislature, the personnel, facilities, and projects of WRL were transferred over to an independent and state-endorsed institute.
In the decade that IST was responsible for WRL, IST had two principal aims: to plan and administer the university's large sponsored research program; and to find seed money for promising research (especially research with specific relevance to the state's economy). In addition, IST administered a number of organizations concerned with inter-disciplinary research, service, and teaching. Mention has already been made of the Biophysics Research Division (BRD) and the Great Lakes Research Division (later to become one of the water-related research units that forms the Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center: GLMWC). Others created during the 1960s and 1970s included the Industrial Development Division (IDD), the Highway Safety Research Institute, the Macromolecular Research Center (MACRO), and the MERIT Computer Network. By 1985, there were eight units of this sort, not counting units that had been operated within IST, and then had either been phased out or transferred to different University units. These eight units, in addition to BRD, GLMWC, IDD, and MACRO, were the Computer Network Division (CND) which had assumed most of the responsibilities of MERIT, the Transportation Research Institute (UMTRI), which was the successor of the Highway Safety Research Institute, the Center for Catalysis and Surface Science, and the Special Projects Division (SPD), which was created in 1982 to nurture new areas of research and to house special programs not easily accommodated elsewhere in IST, such as the Ultra-Small Structures Research Office.
As a unit with disparate and shifting areas of interest (albeit most of them falling within areas of intercooperative research), IST often reviewed its activities and defined its goals. In the 1980s, in part because of the university's efforts to "downsize," IST underwent a series of faculty examinations and unit reviews. The ultimate result was that the Regents, at their meeting of October 1987, approved 1) the transfer of a number of units to elsewhere within the university or establishing them as free-standing units, and 2) the reorganization of the Office of the Vice President for Research "so as to create two foci, one for interdisciplinary research activities and the other for economic and industrial development activities." The aim of this reorganization was to revitalize the various units, to improve the linkages that exist between the units and the faculty, and to improve the lines of authority through which these research units reported to the university's administration. The Regents made clear that the units provide a valuable function, and were not being abandoned, but just shuffled about administratively.
At this writing (December 1989), IST consists of six research divisions: Biophysics Research Division, Center for Catalysis and Surface Science, Center for Molecular Genetics, Macromolecular Research Center, Program in Protein Structure and Design, and Technology Transfer Center.
Directors of the Institute of Science and Technology
1959-1960 Robert R. White
1960-1962 Joseph A. Boyd
1962-1964 James T. Wilson (Acting)
1964-1978) James T. Wilson
1978-1981) Joseph J. Martin (Acting)
1981-1986 George Gamota
1986-1987) William C. Kelly (Interim)
1987-1988 Ronald H. Olsen (Acting)
1988- Ronald H. Olsen
The records of the Institute of Science and Technology of the University of Michigan cover the period 1959 to 1987, from the establishment of the unit to the year of its regentally-approved reorganization. Scattered documents prior to 1959 and after 1987 will be found, but not in great quantity.
The record group consists of thirteen series. Except for some modifications and combining of similar materials, these are series that were maintained by the institute office. Types of documents present within these series include memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, budgetary and financial papers, correspondence, proposal and grant documents, subject files, and photographs. The researcher should note that much material was retained by the IST office at the time of the 1989 transfer of records to the library. Thus, records for expected areas of interest might still be in the possession of IST. Periodic additions to this record group are expected.
Although of obvious value for its documentation of the history and activities of IST, the records of the institute have prime interest for the researcher interested in the study of research at a major educational institution. In particular, the records of IST document the development of the relationship between a university and state and national governments for the purpose of fostering research in areas deemed mutually advantageous. On the national level, especially in the 1960s, this research centered on areas of national defense and environmental study. On the state level, research was intended to improve the economy: to develop the state's technological and industrial base, thereby reducing the debilitating consequences of depression and unemployment that had periodically plagued Michigan's one-industry economy.
Of some value for the study of the content of research undertaken under IST auspices, the records here are of greater importance for the study of the environment required for research programs to be successful. The specifics of research will be found in scientific notebooks, laboratory experiments, and published studies. The IST records document a different story: the need to search out, administer, and balance competing requests for funding, space, equipment, and trained personnel. The IST files, in effect, document the management of research.
Beyond these research possibilities, the records of IST are illustrative of the changing patterns of technological research over the past thirty years. Founded with specific economic goals in mind, IST (with the administrative transfer of Willow Run Laboratories) managed programs having national defense implications. With the completion of these programs, and especially as the university ceased its responsibility for Willow Run, IST turned to areas of new research or areas of special significance to Michigan (perhaps the most notable examples being in the areas of highway safety and water-related research).
Subjects:
Great Lakes (North America); Michigan Sea Grant Program.; Research.; Research institutes.; Research vessels.; University of Michigan. Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center.; University of Michigan. Great Lakes Resource Management Program.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology. Industrial Development Division.; University of Michigan--Research.; University of Michigan. Transportation Research Institute.; University of Michigan. Willow Run Laboratories.; Water.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Laboratories.; Research facilities.; University of Michigan. Willow Run Laboratories.; Videotapes.; North Campus (University of Michigan)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- History/Informational Files
  History/Informational Files (.8 linear feet) is comprised of collected documents, memoranda, clippings, and other materials relating to the organization, history, and accomplishments of IST; some of this material was accumulated as part of presentations by IST to university administrators and other visitors.
  - Historical information and memorabilia, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - IST organization file (Box 1)
  - Informational file given to George Gamota upon his arrival (Box 1)
  - Memoranda (James Wilson) re. IST (Box 1)
  - Informational file largely re. Willow Run Laboratories (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Newsletter News in Brief, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Accession: history and background materials, 1990; 10 folders (Box 1)
- Reports
  The series Reports, 1959-1985. (0.3 linear feet) includes annual reports submitted to the President of the University of Michigan; also occasional reports and briefings submitted to the Regents of the university and to the governor of the state on the progress and programs of IST.
  - Reports to the President (UM) (Box 33)
    - 1959-1987/88, 5 folders (Box 33)
  - Progress Report to the Governor, November 1960 (Box 33)
  - Briefing of the Regents on the Aims and Programs of IST, December 1960 (Box 33)
  - Memorandum to Governor John Swainson on the IST Research Program, September 1961 (Box 33)
- Executive Committee
  The Executive Committee, 1959-1987 series (0.7 linear feet) consists of yearly files (except for 1972) of minutes, agenda, and some informational documents of the executive committee of IST; also subject files relating to matters of job title and classification.
  - Minutes, agenda, etc., 1959-1987; 35 folders (Box 33)
    (Note: 1972 file missing)
  - Subject files
    - Adjunct titles (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
    - Membership (Box 2)
    - Peer Review Committee (Box 2)
    - Research Scientist classification (Box 2)
    - Sabbatical leave program (Box 2)
- Institute Reviews
  Institute Reviews, 1974-1988 (0.5 linear feet) includes statements, reports, and background material relating to the various reviews of the purpose and aims of IST.
  - Review statement, August 1974 (Box 2)
  - Review Committee, 1978
    - Report and Executive Committee comments on report (Box 2)
    - Charges to Review Committee; minutes of Review Committee (Box 2)
    - Material furnished Review Committee (Box 2)
    - Historical Material (Box 2)
  - Task Force (correspondence and report), 1983; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Review Committee, 1985-1986
    - Advisory Committee on evaluation of IST (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
    - Committee tour of IST, November 1985 (Box 2)
  - Review Committee (cont.), 1985-1986
    - Background material assembled for meeting with the Review Committee, November 1985 (Box 2)
    - Report (Box 2)
    - Comments on Report (Box 2)
    - Realignment files, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Unit Reviews
  Unit Reviews, 1983-1988 (0.5 linear feet) Contains reports, correspondence, memoranda, and other documents relating to the administrative reviews made of IST's research units.
  - General, 1983-1986 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Development Division and Special Projects Division (pre-transition material), 1987 (Box 2)
  - Biophysics Research Division review, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes and Marine Waters Center
    - Review Report, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Transition file, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
      (also concerns Great Lakes Research Division)
  - Great Lakes Research Division (pre-transition team) (Box 2)
  - Industrial Development Division review, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Macromolecular Research Center
    - Review, 1988 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Transportation Research Institute, 1984-1985 (Box 3)
- Budgets, Funds, Accounts
  The series Budgets, Funds, Accounts, 1959-1986 (0.7 linear feet) consists of yearly files of budget and budget activity information; also subject files relating to such topics as audits, discretionary funds, and other funding information.
  - General Fund Budget and Budget Activity, 1959/60-1985/86; 35 folders (Box 3)
  - Topical files
    - Application the State of Michigan for Tax Credit Account under Public Act 315, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Audits of IST done by Internal Audits of the UM, 1978-1984 (Box 3)
    - Audits-21 (IDC), February 1985 (Box 3)
    - Budget Procedures, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
    - Discretionary Funds
      - Announcements of IST Programs to UM departments and other Michigan colleges and universities, 1959-1961 (Box 3)
      - Budget priorities, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Criteria for Reviewing Requests for Funds, 1959-1985 (Box 3)
      - Liaison Committee of Michigan Schools and Colleges, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Discretionary Funds
      - Policy and correspondence from other Michigan colleges on funding requests, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
      - Summaries of funds awarded, 1959-1980 (Box 3)
      - Survey of faculty members who received released time from OVPR, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Five-year plan
      - 1982, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1983 (Box 3)
    - Fringe benefit and indirect cost computation for IST, 1969-1980 (Box 3)
    - Indirect cost computation-effort reports for department administration, 1966-1975 (Box 3)
    - List of expendable fund accounts (Box 3)
    - List of general fund accounts (Box 3)
    - Organization codes for IST accounts (Box 3)
    - Priority funds, 1978-1980 (Box 3)
    - Suggestion for funds (includes correspondence with Wernher von Braun re. visit to IST in 1960) (Box 3)
- Director's Staff Meetings
  The Directors' Staff Meetings series, 1981-1987 (1 linear foot) includes notebooks containing minutes, agenda, and background materials discussed at meetings of the directors of IST's research units.
  - Notebooks containing minutes, agenda, and background materials, 1981-1987; 6 volumes (Box 4)
  - Subgroup re. increased UM/industry interactions, 1983; 1 folders (Box 4)
- Director's Office Files
  The Director's Office Files constitutes the central office file of IST directors from 1959-1988. The series is organized into two subseries: 1959-ca. 1980 and 1970-1988 reflecting the accessions in which the files were transferred to the library.
  - 1959-circa 1980
    The Directors Office Files, 1959-ca. 1980 (2.7 linear feet) are arranged alphabetically, this series best documents the management of IST by its various directors. Interesting files here relate to the debate over the university's policy on classified research, and to the administration of research undertaken at Willow Run Laboratories in the 1960s.
    - Ann Arbor Chamber of Commerce Economic Development Committee, 1965; 1977 (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor Industry Presidents Association, 1980 (Box 5)
    - Argonne Universities Association-Tripartite Contract, 1966; 1974 (Box 5)
    - Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Building (IST)
      - Historical materials (Box 5)
      - Statistical reports, space allocations, etc. (Box 5)
      - Open House, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Center for Research Park, 1961-1963 (Box 5)
    - Classified Research
      - UM Policy on Classified Research, 1972 (Box 5)
      - Reaction from faculty and staff, 1957-1971 (Box 5)
      - At other universities (Box 5)
      - At Stanford Research Institute (Box 5)
      - Correspondence with government offices, 1967-1971 (Box 5)
    - Classified Research
      - Statistics (Box 5)
      - Clippings and articles, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Committee on relationships between UM and the State Board of Education, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Conductron, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
    - Contacts
      - Educational (outside) contacts, 1961; 1974 (Box 5)
      - Industrial contacts, 1963-1968 (Box 5)
      - Governor's Office and Science Advisory Board, 1960-1962 (Box 5)
      - Council of Institutions, 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Department of Commerce
      - Conference on University-Industry Program Directors, 1965 (Box 5)
      - Detroit Area Conference on Industrial Modernization, 1965 (Box 5)
      - Proposed Civilian Industrial Technology Program, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Department of Interior
      - Geological Survey, 1964-1968 (Box 5)
    - Detroit East Side Development, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Earth Resources Satellite Program, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Eastern Michigan University, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Economic Advisory Panel, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Educom, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - Electronics Industry Conference
      - 1961 (Box 5)
      - 1962 (Box 5)
    - Energy Research and Development Administration, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Basin Commission, 1967-1970 (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Foundation, 1966-1971 (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Foundation (articles of incorporation and bylaws) (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Foundation (demise), 1971-1974 (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Research Division, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Great Lakes Research Symposium, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Hart, Philip A., 1962 (Box 5)
    - High Level Conference, 1980 (Box 5)
    - IMPETUS, Inc., 1962-1963 (Box 6)
    - Industrial development research program, 1960-1963; 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Institute for Defense Analyses, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Irwin International Industries, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Marine Technology Society, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Material sciences programs, 1959-1968 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Department of Economic Development, 1963-1972 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Energy and Resource Research Association (MERRA), 1975-1982 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Energy Study, 1960-1962 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Industrial Ambassadors, 1961 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Industry-University Research Conference, 1962-1964 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Science Advisory Board, 1959 (Box 6)
    - Michigan State University (proposed links with IST), 1960-1962 (Box 6)
    - Michigan State University-Study of the impact of federal support of science on universities and colleges in Michigan, 1966-1968 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Technological University, 1960-1962 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Week, 1962-1963 (Box 6)
    - North Campus planning, 1965-1981 (Box 6)
    - Nuclear Service Center, 1961 (Box 6)
    - Office of Technology Assessment, 1978 (Box 6)
    - Organizational charts (Box 6)
    - Press releases, 1959-1961 (Box 6)
    - Research development authority legislation, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Schools and Colleges Liaison Committee, 1960-1972 (Box 6)
    - South Eastern Metropolitan Community Research Committee, 1961 (Box 6)
    - Speeches, articles, etc. (primarily Robert R. White, Joseph A. Boyd, and James T. Wilson), 1959-1963; 13 folders (Box 6)
    - Technology-based Industry Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
    - Tours and displays (Box 6)
    - Upper Atmosphere Research Corp., 1973 (Box 6)
    - Upper Great Lakes Regional Commission, 1967 (Box 6)
    - UM Washington Office, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
    - Wayne State University, 1960-1965 (Box 6)
    - Willow Run Laboratories (Box 7)
      - Administration (general) (Box 7)
      - AMOS Project, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
      - Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (formerly Michigan Research Institute; formed in when the UM terminated its contract research at Willow Run Laboratories), 1973
        - Miscellaneous, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
        - Published materials and resolution creating MRI (Box 7)
      - Expendable Restricted Accounts and Financial Reports, 1963-1970 (Box 7)
      - Holography, 1964-1979 (Box 7)
      - Infrared and Optical Sensor Laboratory, 1963-1968 (Box 7)
      - Macnee Committee (Ad hoc Committee on Large Laboratory Operations), 1969-1970 (Box 7)
      - Novation agreement, 1972 (Box 7)
      - Office of Economic Development negotiations, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
      - Project MICHIGAN, 1963-1968 (Box 7)
      - Radar and Optics Laboratory, 1961-1968 (Box 7)
      - Remote Sensing
        - General, 1966-1969 (Box 7)
        - Center for Remote Sensing Information and Analysis, 1966-1968 (Box 7)
        - NASA Workshop on Remote Sensing, 1971 (Box 7)
        - Remote Sensing Symposia, 1962-1973 (Box 7)
      - Reorganization
        - Fleming Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 7)
        - Correspondence and memoranda, 1969-1971 (Box 7)
        - Reactions ("Comments on the transition of the Willow Run Laboratories to the Research Institute of Michigan" by William M. Brown, 1972) (Box 7)
        - Reactions (newspaper clippings and articles) (Box 7)
        - Transition file (Box 7)
      - Research projects, 1963-1973 (Box 7)
      - Willow Run properties, 1960-1970 (Box 7)
  - circa 1979-1988